Guide to the David Olson Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
- David Olson papers, 1937-2006; 1994-2006; 5672-002; 2.57 cubic feet 3 boxes
  - "Dockers versus the Directive--The War on Europe's Waterfront"--Peter Turnball, Cadiff University, approximately 2006 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Leadership Education and Development Institute, approximately 2005-2005 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - "International Longshore and Warehouse Union's Refusal to Comply with Temporary Restraining Order and Preliminary Injunction in West Coast Ports--United States of America v. Pacific Maritime Association and International Longshore and Warehouse Union", 2002 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Research and Presentation Materials: Labor Law and Development Prepared by Rob Remar, International Longshore and Warehouse Union Longshore Division and Contract, and Cargo-Handling Terms, approximately 2002 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Assorted Correspondence, Research Procedures, and Notes: "Union Democracy Reexamined"--Margaret Levi, David Olson, Jon Agnone, and Devin Kelly, approximately 2005-2006 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Writing and Correspondence: "Union Democracy Reexamined"--Margaret Levi, David Olson, Jon Agnone, and Devin Kelly, approximately 2006-2008 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - International Longshore and Warehouse Union and Pacific Maritime Association Related Subject Materials: Draft of "Showdown on the Waterfront: The 2002 West Coast Port Dispute"--Kathleen McGuinn and Dina Witter, 2004 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Notes, Research, Correspondence, Consulting, Presentation Materials, and International Longshore and Warehouse Union Research Including: International Longshore and Warehouse Union and Pacific Maritime Association Lockout, "Mayor James K. Hahn and Mayor B, approximately 2002-2006 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - "International Longshore and Warehouse Union Education Seminar History and Traditions of the Longshore Division--Palm Springs, California", 2004 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Budget, Research, Procedures, Planning, and Correspondence for "Union Democracy Reexamined", 2005 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - "Some Comments by Sam Kagel on the History of the International Longshore and Warehouse Union and Pacific Maritime Agreements 1932-1972"--Sam Kagel, approximately 1995 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - "Erosion of Trade Union Freedom Under the Law Undelivered Remarks (c. 1988) by Jimmy Herman, International Longshore and Warehouse Union International President, 1971-1991, Edited by Rob Remar, International Longshore and Warehouse Union Counsel", approximately 1988 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Notes with Photocopies of The Dispatcher, 1947-1961 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Research Materials: International Longshoremen's Association Pacific Coast District Balloting Results, International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union Referendum Ballots and Election Returns, The Dispatcher Locals Voting and Results, approximately 1937-1971 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Research Materials: The Dispatcher Printed with "How Locals Voted on Officers, Executive Board, and Coast Committee" (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Research Materials: History of Registration and Membership of the International Longshore and Warehouse Union, and the "Pacific Maritime ASsociation 1998 Annual Report", 1937-1998 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Email Correspondence Between Margaret Levi, David Olson, and Gene Vrana: "Longshore Traditions Conference" and Related Materials, approximately 2001-2004 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - "Inducing Preferences Within Organizations: The Case of Unions"--Margaret Levi, with Notes by David Olson, 2003 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - International Longshore and Warehouse Union: "1994 International and Coast Committee Referendum Elections", "Report of the International Balloting Committee"--1997, "History of Shoreside Registration - By Occupation by International Longshore and Wareho, 1945; approximately 1994-1997 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Research Materials: International Longshore and Warehouse Union Election Dataset Codebook"--Heather A. Larsen, "Average Membership Pacific Coast Longshore and Ship Clerks Locals, ILWU 1946-1949", "The Party Circuit"--Arther Schlesinger Jr., Emails, and N, 1946-1949; 1995-2004 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - "From Wharf Rats to Lords of the Dock" Pamphlet, Harry Bridges Institute News, and "How the Union Works"--The Dispatcher, 1994-2005 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Letters: Search Committee for Executive Directors of Washington Public Ports Association, 1992 September 30-October 13 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Pat Parrish Lee Speech, 7th Draft: "Managing Alaska Ports and Terminals Presented to Operations and Finance Panel at Maritime Alaska '81 Conference, September 22, 1981", Approximately 1981 September (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Letters of thanks from Pat Davis, Port Commissioner, to David Olson for campaign contributions, 1997 August 18 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Comparative Analysis of West Coast Ports, Michael Denning, David Olson, 1988 November (Box-folder 2/4)
  - An Assessment of Strategic Issues, Commission Session, Michael Denning and David Olson (Port of Seattle), 1995 October 3 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - ODYSSEY, The Maritime Discovery Center. Pamphlet, letters concerning David Olson's joining Odyssey Board of Directors, Nominating Committee Report, David Olson's resignation from the Board., 2001 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Letter from Patricia Davis, Commissioner of Port of Seattle, to David, included photograph, 1988 October 16 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Correspondence with Port of Seattle from David Olson's files, 1979 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Letters from David Olson to Port of Seattle regarding publication of "Comparative Analysis of West Coast Ports", 1988 October 26-November 16 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Contract with Port of Seattle (letters, memos, June 1982 issue of Import, 1979 July 24-1987 August 25 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Correspondence with the University of Washington, 1979 January 24-1980 April 18 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Port In a Storm, An Historical Review of the Founding of the Port of Seattle" Includes a separate 2 page forward by Richard D. Ford. published 2010, March 29, 1981 September 5; 2010 March 29 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Executive Director Richard Ford's Retirement from Port of Seattle and Appointment as Faculty at University of Washington, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - David Olson Papers: "Governance of US Public Ports: A Preliminary Survey of Key Issues", Executive Officer Appraisal Systems","Public Port Accountability", Approximately 1990-1992 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - David Olson's Correspondence. Includes emails, press releases from the Port of Seattle, letter from Tay Yoshitani, publicity items describing 1007 Port performance, preparation for panel discussion (Comparative Analysis of Seattle and Los Angeles) in Los, 2006-2008 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Union Democracy Reexamined, Margaret Levi, David Olson and their Team. Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies. University of Washington, Seattle, 2004 September 27 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Quote (David Olson): Single copied page titled "Labor" about ILWU members. "They see themselves as lords of the docks." Book not named, no page number, Approximately 1985-2005 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Letters among David Olson, Margaret Levi, Joe Wenzl, Gene Vrana. (Includes handwritten note about 1/15/03 phone conversation), 2003 January 15-2004 January 4 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Letters in preparation for the International Longshore and Warehouse Union Conference Education Seminar on the History and Traditions of the ILWU Longshore Division, beginning January 15, 2004., 2003 November 26 - December 5 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - "Instructors outline" ILWU Leadership Education and Development Institute: Tools and Traditions of Democracy. Palm Springs, California, 2005 September 19-23 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Letter exchange: Peter Saltzman and David Olson, after tentative settlement: United States v. Pacific Maritime Association et al (and one short, handwritten note itemizing legal charges), 2002 November 12-December 10 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - David Olson's Sabbatical Leave Application.to the University of Washington to serve as Visiting Scholar at the University of California, Berkeley in 1995 - 1996, 1994 October 25 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Lecture notes, printed and handwritten, email arranging attendance, ILWU printed materials (All found clipped together in David Olson's files), 2008 (Box-folder 2/23)
  - The 2002 ILWU Contract: Evolving Industrial Relations Among West Coast USA Longshore Workers. David J. Olson, 2006 May (Box-folder 2/24)
  - "Administration should keep clear of dock fight." by David J. Olson, Special to The Times, Approximately 2002 (Box-folder 2/25)
  - Letter from University of Washington Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies offering David P. Olson a research grant., 2002 August 28 (Box-folder 2/26)
  - Journal of Commerce article: Why locals rejected ILWU contract" by Bill Mongelluzzo, 1996 August 23 (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Purposes and Objectives (Port of Seattle): Printed information, pamphlets, letters Including letter of agreement to Professor Olson to hire him as research consultant, certificate of appreciation., 1980 (Box-folder 2/28)
  - University of Alaska: Correspondence regarding "Maritime Alaska '81, Maritime Commerce and Port Development Conference" in Anchorage, 1981 (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Port Governance Roundtable Agenda, 1992 November 10 (Box-folder 2/30)
  - League of Women Voters of the San Juans. Announcement of David Olson's presentation, and news release, 1993 September 11 (Box-folder 2/31)
  - U.S. Public Enterprise: Accountability and Efficiency, David J. Olson. Table of contents, approximately 1992-1993 (Box-folder 2/32)
  - Letter from David J. Olson to Paige Miller of the Port of Seattle Commission, regarding the appraisal system for the Executive Officer of the Port of Seattle, 1992 March 16 (Box-folder 2/33)
  - David Olson's letter to Mic R. Dinsmore, recommending that the Port of Seattle recognize Richard D. Ford's career and contributions, 2005 March 28 (Box-folder 2/34)
  - International Longshore and Warehouse Union letter of thanks from Gene Vrana to David J. Olson. (Mentions the video WE ARE THE ILWU, and David Olson's recent cancer diagnosis), 1997 November 20 (Box-folder 2/35)
  - Letter from David J. Olson to James D. Dwyer of Washington Dental Service regarding retainer for consulting services, 2003 October 30`` (Box-folder 2/36)
  - ILWU Leadership Education and Development Institute. Outline for presentations at Palm Springs, California scheduled for September 19 through 23, 2005, 2005 September (Box-folder 2/37)
  - The Processing of Racial Crisis in America. Michael Lipsky and David J. Olson, Politics and Society 6, pages 79-103, 1976 (Box-folder 2/38)
  - CITIZEN GRIEVANCE LETTERS AS A GUBERNATORIAL CONTROL DEVICE IN WISCONSIN. David J. Olson, Indiana University, Journal of Politics, Volume 31, 1969 (Box-folder 2/39)
  - INTRODUCING PREFERENCES WITHIN ORGANIZATIONS: THE CASE OF UNIONS. Margaret Levi, Professor of International Studies, University of Washington. Working Paper number 16, 2003 February (Box-folder 2/40)
  - Ghetto Revolts. Edited by Peter H. Rossi. Published by Aldine Publishing Company. Copyright 1970 (Box-folder 2/41)
  - Discourse...A Review of the Liberal Arts, Winter 1970. Volume XIII, No. 1 (article by David J. Olson on pages 20 - 27: Changing Political Processes, Channels, Structures and the System.) (Box-folder 2/42)
  - RIOT COMMISSION POLITICS, Institute for research on POVERTY. Michael Lipsky and David J. Olson. The University of Wisconsin, Volume 6, No. 9, July - August, 1969 (Box-folder 2/43)
  - WORKING USA, The Journal of Labor and Society, Winter 2002 - 3 (Article: Living Wage Campaigns and Laws, by Margaret Levi, David J. Olson, and Erich Steinmen, pages 111 - 132), 2002-2003 (Box-folder 2/44)
  - Indiana University Founder Day Ceremonial (booklet with pamphlets, news articles, color photographs, letter from David Sandee Maia found tucked into its pages), 1973 April 18 (Box-folder 2/45)
  - INSTITUTE FOR RESEARCH ON POVERTY. On the Politics of Riot Commissions, Michael Lipsky and David J. Olson. DISCUSSION PAPERS, the University of Wisconsin. Prepared for presentation at the Meeting of the American Political Science Association, September 3, 1968 (Box-folder 2/46)
  - DID BANFIELD RUN RIOT IN WRITING "RIOTING MAINLY FOR FUN AND PROFIT"? David J. Olson, Indiana University (revised version of paper delivered in 1971) (Box-folder 2/47)
  - Transaction, Social Science and Modern Society, July/August, 1969. Article by Michael Lipsky and David J. Olson: RIOT COMMISSION POLITICS found on pages 9 - 21 (Box-folder 2/48)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: Personal Letters and Messages, approximately 1959-1973 (Box-folder 2/49)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: Newspaper Articles Featuring David Olson, approximately 1951-1982 (Box-folder 2/50)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: 3 Washington Apples advertising posters. Yakima and Tieton, Washington, approximately 1959-1973 (Box-folder 2/51)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: Photographs of David Olson as a Child and Teen, approximately 1951-1960 (Box-folder 2/52)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: Photographs of David Olson and Classmates at Concordia, approximately 1962-1963 (Box-folder 2/53)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: The Black Family Reunion at Juanita Lake, North Dakota- Program and Historic Family Photo Print Outs., 2009 July 18-19 (Box-folder 2/54)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: West Fargo High School Class of 1959, 25th Reunion Booklet, 1984 (Box-folder 2/55)
  - Scrapbook Loose Items: West Fargo High School Class of 1959 20th and 25th Reunion Group Photographs, 1979, 1984 (Box-folder 2/56)
  - Indiana University Faculty Newsletter, Vol. XXI, No. 9 Featuring Article on David Olson and Distinguished Teaching Award, 1973 May 11 (Box-folder 2/57)
  - Scrapbook of David Olson's Years at Concordia College, Moorhead Minnesota: Newsclippings and Memorabilia, approximately 1961-1963 (Box-folder 3/1)